all librivox recordings are In the public domain for more information or to
volunteer please visit librivox.org the Wizard of Oz Chapter 2 The Council with
the Munchkins She was awakened by a shock, so sudden and severe that if
Dorothy had not been lying on the soft bed she might have been hurt. As it was,
the jar made her catch her breath and wonder what had happened; and Toto put
his cold little nose into her face and whine dismally. Dorothy set up and
noticed that the house was not moving; nor was it dark, for the bright sunshine
came in at the window, flooding the little room. She sprang from her bed and
with Toto at her heels ran and opened the door. The little girl gave a cry of
amazement and looked about her, her eyes growing bigger and bigger at the
wonderful sight she saw.
The cyclone had set the house down very gently— —for a cyclone— —in the midst of a
country of marvellous beauty. There were lovely patches of green sward all about,
with stately trees bearing rich and luscious fruits. Banks of gorgeous
flowers were on every hand, and birds with rare and brilliant plumage sang and
fluttered in the trees and bushes. A little way off was a small brook, rushing
and sparkling along between green banks, and murmuring in a voice very grateful
to a little girl who had lived so long on the dry, gray prairie While she stood
looking eagerly at the strange and beautiful sights, she noticed coming
toward her a group of the queerest people she had ever seen. They were not
as big as the grown folk she had always been used to; but neither were they very
small. In fact, they seemed about as tall as Dorothy, who was a well grown child
for her age, although they were, so far as looks go, many years older. Three were men
and one a woman, and all were oddly dressed.
They wore round hats that rose to a small point a foot above their heads,
with little bells around the brims that tinkled sweetly as they moved. The hats
of the men were blue; the little woman’s hat was white, and she wore a white gown
that hung in pleats from her shoulders.
Over it were sprinkled little stars that glistened in the sun like diamonds. The
men were dressed in blue, of the same shade as their hats, and wore well
polished boots with a deep roll of blue at the tops. The men, Dorothy thought, were
about as old as Uncle Henry, for two of them had beards. But the little woman was
doubtless much older. Her face was covered with wrinkles,
her hair was nearly white, and she walked rather stiffly. When these people drew
near the house where Dorothy was standing in the doorway, they paused and
whispered among themselves, as if afraid to come farther. But the little old woman
walked up to Dorothy, made a low bow and said, in a sweet voice: “You are welcome,
most noble Sorceress, to the land of the Munchkins. We are so grateful to you for
having killed the at Witch of the East, and for setting our
people free from bondage.” Dorothy listen to this speech with wonder. What could
the little woman possibly mean by calling her a sorceress, and saying she
had killed the Wicked Witch of the East?
Dorothy was an innocent, harmless little girl, who had been carried by cyclone
many miles from home; and she had never killed anything in all her life. But the
little woman evidently expected her to answer; so Dorothy said, with hesitation,
“You are very kind, but there must be some mistake. I have not killed anything.” “Your
house did, anyway,” replied the little old woman, with a laugh, “and that is the same
thing. See!” she continued, pointing to the corner of the house. “There are her two
feet, still sticking out from under a block of wood.” Dorothy looked, and gave a
little cry of fright.
There, indeed, just under the corner of the great bean the house rested on, two
feet were sticking out, shod and silver shoes with pointed toes. “Oh, dear! Oh, dear!”
cried Dorothy, clasping her hands together in dismay. “The house must have
fallen on her. Whatever shall we do?” “There is nothing to be done,” said the little
woman calmly. “But who was she?” asked Dorothy. “She was the Wicked Witch of the East,
as I said,” answered the little woman. “She has held all the Munchkins in bondage
for many years, making them slave for her night and day. Now they are all set free,
and are grateful to you for the favor.” “Who are the Munchkins?” inquired Dorothy.
“They are the people who live in this land of the East where the Wicked Witch
ruled.” “Are you a Munchkin?” asked Dorothy.
“No, but I am their friend, although I live in the land of the North. When they saw
the Witch of the East was dead the munchkin sent a swift messenger to me,
and I came at once. I am the Witch of the North.”
“Oh, gracious!” cried Dorothy. “Are you a real witch?” “Yes, indeed,” answered the little
woman. “But I'm a good witch, and the people love me. I am not as powerful as
the Wicked Witch was who ruled here, or I should have said to people free myself.”
“But I thought all witches were wicked,” said the girl, who was half frightened at
facing a real witch. “Oh, no, that is a great mistake.
There were only four witches in all the Land of Oz, and two of them, those who
live in the North and the South, are good
witches. I know this is true, for I am one of them myself, and cannot be mistaken.
Those who dwell in the East and the West were, indeed, wicked witches; but now that
you have killed one of them there's but one Wicked Witch in all the Land of Oz—
—the one who lives in the West.” “But Dorothy said after a moment’s thought
and gem has told me that the witches were all dead—
—years and years ago.” “Who is nm inquired the little old woman. “She is my aunt who
lives in Kansas, where I come from.” The Witch of the North seemed to think for a
time, with her head bowed and her eyes upon the ground. Then she looked up and
said, “I do not know where Kansas is, for I have never heard that country mentioned
before. But tell me, is it a civilized country?” “Oh, yes,” replied Dorothy. “Then that
accounts for it. In the civilized countries I believe there are no witches
left, nor wizards, nor Sorceress's norma jiton x' But, you see, the Land of Oz has
never been civilized, for we are cut off from all the rest of the world. Therefore
we still have witches and wizards amongst us.” “Who are the wizards?” asked
Dorothy. “Oz himself is the Great Wizard,” answered the Witch, sinking her voice to
a whisper. “He is more powerful than all the rest of us together. He lives in the
City of Emeralds.” Dorothy was going to ask another question, but just then the
Munchkins, who had been standing silently by, gave a loud shout and pointed to the
corner of the house where the Wicked Witch had been lying. “What is it?” asked
the little old woman, and looked, and began to laugh. The feet of the dead
Witch had disappeared entirely, and nothing was left but the silver shoes.
“She was so old,” explained the Witch of the North, “that she dried up quickly in
the sun. That is the end of her. But the silver shoes are you
roars and you shall have them to where She reached down and picked up the shoes,
and after shaking the dust out of them handed them to Dorothy. “The Witch of the
East was proud of those silver shoes,” said one of the Munchkins, “and there are
some charm connected with them; but what it is we never knew.” Dorothy carried the
shoes into the house and placed them on the table. Then she came out again to the
Munchkins and said: “I am anxious to get back to my aunt and uncle, for I am sure
they will worry about me. Can you help me find my way?” The Munchkins in the which
first looked at one another, and then at Dorothy, and then shook their heads. “At
the East, not far from here,” said one, “there is a great desert, and none could
live to cross it.” “It is the same at the South,” said another, “for I have been there
and seen it. The South is the country of the Quadlings.” “I am told,” said the third
man, “that is the same at the West. And that country, where the Winkies live, is
ruled by the Wicked Witch of the West, who would make you her slave if you
passed her way.” “The North is my home,” said
the old lady, “and at its edge is the same great desert that surrounds this Land of
Oz. I’m afraid, my dear, you will have to live with us.” Dorothy began to sob at
this, for she felt lonely among all these strange people. Her tears seemed to
grieve the kind-hearted Munchkins, for they immediately took out their
handkerchiefs and began to weep also. As for the little old woman, she took off
her cap and balanced the point on the end of her nose, while she counted “One,
two, three” in a solemn voice. At once the cap changed to a slate, on which was
written in big, white chalk marks: “LET DOROTHY GO TO THE CITY OF EMERALDS” The
little old woman took the slate from her nose, and having read the words on it,
asked, “Is your name Dorothy, my dear?” “Yes,” answered the child, looking up and drying
her tears. “Then you must go to the City of Emeralds.
Perhaps Oz will help you.” “Where is this city?” asked Dorothy. “It is exactly in the
center of the tree and is ruled by Oz, the Great Wizard
I told you of.” “Is he a good man?” inquired the girl anxiously. “He is a good Wizard.
Whether he is a man or not I cannot tell, for I have never seen him.”
“How can I get there?” asked Dorothy. “You must walk. It is a long journey, through a
country that is sometimes pleasant and sometimes dark and terrible. However, I
will use all the magic arts I know of to
keep you from harm.” “Won’t you go with me?” pleaded the girl, who had begun to look
upon the little old woman as her only friend.
“No, I cannot do that,” she replied, “but I will give you my kiss, and no one will
dare injure a person who has been kissed by the Witch of the North.”
She came close to Dorothy and kissed her gently on the forehead. Where her lips
touched the girl they left a round shiny mark, as Dorothy found out soon after. “The
road to the City of Emeralds is paved with yellow brick,” said the Witch, “so you
cannot miss it. When you get to Oz do not
be afraid of him, but tell your story and
ask him to help you good bye my dear.” The three Munchkins bowed low to her and
wished her a pleasant journey, after which they walked away through the trees.
The Witch gave Dorothy a friendly little nod, whirled around on her left heel
three times, and straight away disappeared, much to the surprise of
little Toto, who barked after her loudly enough when she had gone, because he had
been afraid even to growl while she stood by. But Dorothy, knowing her to be a
witch, had expected her to disappear in just that way, and was not surprised in
the least end of chapter 2